The stock market was going to boom
either way. Payrolls could have come in
at plus 200,000 or minus 200,000 and it
wouldn't have made a difference. Indexes
were going to soar no matter what.
Either the economy's robust or if the
other one, then the Federal Reserve
would be forced to cut rates and buy a
lot. Stocks couldn't possibly lose here.
But what the actual data showed was a
complete shock. Yes, payrolls did what
payrolls always do. The rest of the
data, however, no one was looking for
this.
The real details, the one that you need
to pay attention to, they have nothing
to do with the headline establishment
survey. They The household survey
version of employment contracted by more
than 200,000. In fact, it was the third
straight month of contraction in
employment. The unemployment rate was
steady, but as we know, the reason the
unemployment rate was steady is because
even more American workers, I guess
former American workers, dropped out of
the labor force yet again. So, our
adjusted unemployment rate hit 5.8%
a new high. Not a new high, you can see
the difference between what we think is
employment unemployment and what the
official number is, 4.3. So, you got a
point and a half difference there, which
is one reason why people are confused
about the economic situation. And some
people who are not confused about the
economic situation are those at the
University of Michigan ask, "How are you
doing in this economy?" And they said
at a record pace, we are not doing well.
The University of Michigan consumer
confidence numbers come in record lows,
not a surprise there given the job
market, the real situation of the job
market, not to mention prospects for $5
gasoline. It's a pretty bad time to be a
consumer and worker in this economy. And
we should not forget our neighbors to
the north in Canada. They also reported
payroll reports that were equally grim,
which also suggests the numbers we're
getting from the household survey are
more more likely the real picture of the
labor market than the establishment
survey, but then again, we know that.
knowing that for the last couple of
years. So, Mr. Van Meter, we got a whole
slew of data, a whole slew of critical
data from employment we'll start in the
United States. You know, the
establishment survey
no surprise there. I mean, come on. The
establishment survey is going to beat uh
every expectation every single month,
right?
>> Yeah, absolutely, Jeff. I mean, you
could see this coming a mile away. Stock
markets up and of course everybody knows
that the headline survey is the only
thing the stock market cares about. You
give it a beat, stock prices go up,
everybody's happy. But, it's interesting
because you mentioned the University of
Michigan sentiment survey was you've
seen it record lows that not just
current conditions, but expectations,
just everything is terrible. And you
would think, "Well, wait a minute. If
the nonfarm payroll report's publishing,
you know, above trend of or above
consensus numbers, the stock market's
up, why are consumers so unhappy?" But,
it's all in the household survey. And
this is really key because, you know,
they're getting the phone call and
saying, "Hey, what's What do you think
of the labor market?" They say, "What do
you mean? I just lost my job." You know,
so maybe what we're seeing in in the uh
headline number is more part-time
seasonal jobs as we head into the
summer, but real workers that have
full-time jobs are seeing those go away.
And, you know, it makes perfect sense of
what we're seeing you know, in the
reaction of these sentiment surveys. The
only question then becomes is when does
this transmit into a big decrease in
spending?
>> All right now, as we know, I mean, we
talked about this before. We talked
about it just before we started
recording. Consumers are spending on
gasoline. Uh nominal sales look good,
but then you adjust for prices and maybe
not so much. But, Steve, you know,
the establishment survey, it's it looks
good right now, but who knows what it's
going to be in a couple months. And the
perfect example, the February uh figure
which came in ugly to begin with, minus
92,000, that has since been revised by
get this,
60,000 jobs lower. Now, instead of minus
92, it's minus 156. Now, we do have to
point out the uh March figure which was
178 as the uh preliminary estimate, that
was revised upward. But, it was only
revised upward to 185. So, we got minus
60 on February plus a couple thousand
and what is that 7,000 or yeah, 7,000 on
on March. The 115 that we got here for
April, who knows what it's going to be.
I mean, it it could very well be, you
know, minus 60. So, somewhere around
50,000, which would be, by the way,
right around consensus estimate. So,
like Steve said, it's the head the
establishment survey and I think a lot
of people have finally come to grips
with the fact that the establishment
survey has been misleading for so long.
It doesn't really move markets or
opinion or commentary the way that it
used to. It used to be when the
establishment survey came out, people
were glued to back when we used to watch
TV, were glued to the TV, were glued to
social media. Whenever that number came
out, you know, 8:30 in the morning,
boom, everybody was there. The markets
all traded on it. Now, it's sort of
like,
all right, the payroll number's in. What
does the rest of the report actually
say? And that's where the real details
are, as Steve said, these the household
survey. That one lines up much better,
uh especially the adjusted unemployment
rate that we go through with labor the
adjusted for labor force dropouts. That
one lines up really well with consumer
sentiment. Now, this episode is
sponsored by Augusta Precious Metals.
Now, most of what we cover on the show
is how the financial system actually
works, the mechanics, the incentives,
the plumbing. But, one question I get
from everybody is, okay, I understand
everything now, but what do I do with
this? Now, I can't answer that question
for you. Everybody's different. But, one
thing worth understanding is that a lot
of retire retirement accounts are built
around a pretty narrow set of asset
types. And most people never learn what
else is available to them. Physical gold
held in an IRA is one of those options.
Now, whether it makes sense for you,
that's a separate question. And the
reason I'm comfortable pointing people
to Augusta Precious Metals is that their
approach is education first, just like
us at Euro Dollar University. They'll
walk you through how a gold IRA actually
works, the mechanics, the fees, the
custodial side, and let you decide if
it's relevant to your situation. If you
want to learn more, go to Euro Dollar
Gold.com or text Euro to 35052
and they'll send you a free guide. Now,
Augusta Precious Metals is a paid
sponsor and we thank them for their
sponsorship. This is for educational
purposes only and not investment advice.
Consult a qualified financial
professional before making any
investment decisions. You know, maybe
consumer sentiment University of
Michigan is a bit more pessimistic and
dark than the numbers suggest, but you
can see the trends in both of them. Uh
we just talked about this, Steve. You
know,
consumers got really angry and
pessimistic in 2022 when prices soared
ahead for obvious reasons because prices
were going way up and incomes were not
not keeping up any in any shape way,
shape, or form. In 2023,
consumer sentiment started to come back
as consumer price pressures diminished.
Everybody's oh, disinflation.
Disinflation, the end of the rate hike.
So, okay, we can see there's a light at
the end of the tunnel. But, what
happened in 2024? Well, consumer
sentiment started to roll roll over and
had lower again because the job That's
when the job market flipped over to flat
beverage and job losses and lack of, you
know, lack of hiring. So, consumer
sentiment does match up, at least
directionally, with what we're seeing in
the special especially the
establishments or the payroll the
household survey, excuse me. And then
the establishment survey maybe 2 years
from now will say, oh yeah, that was
correct. That was the right picture.
>> Yeah, absolutely, Jeff, because you
know, you you look at the broader trend
here. What do we see with the labor
market? Continuing evidence of weakness.
And of course, the stock market right
now is saying, hey, you know, the the
weakness we had was due to the war and
now that people are spending more money
on gasoline.
>> See, let me let me ask you this, though.
Don't you think part of this is about
it's not weak enough, right? Because we
have it in our mind that weakness means
the payroll report is minus 700,000. And
anything short of minus 700,000, yes,
I'm being I'm hyperbolic here, but
anything short of a big minus, and it
has to be pretty big minus cuz like we
said, the the February number is minus
156 and that wasn't enough. So, I mean
that's that's really the idea, right?
The the the we're conditioned to believe
it's not a huge minus, therefore it must
be okay, must be, you know, pretty good,
right?
>> Yeah, absolutely. Because what did we
say before the show? The stock market
was going to go up no matter what the
number printed. Why is that? Hey, a
positive number that beat consensus,
well, it's bullish. Stocks go up. If the
number would have printed negative, it
would be Kevin Warsh is going to cut
interest rates. That's bullish. So,
therefore, it really didn't matter. But
if you look at it as I was saying, as
you look at the trend of the labor
market, you look at, you know, consumer
expectations down the road, and you
start to wonder is can the stock market
continue to rally? And the answer is
absolutely in the short term. But if the
economy, particularly labor market,
goes, then at some point the stock
market will have a day of reckoning. But
Jeff, as you know, we've seen this back
in the dot-com bubble and the financial
crisis. You know, the the data can can
tell you where things are going, but the
stock market goes up until the party
ends.
>> Yeah, so where's your S&P 8000 hat,
Steve? I mean, are you We got to have
that somewhere around somewhere.
Go get that thing. But that's a that's a
huge important point. Um
the stock market is detached from
reality. It's detached from any kind of
fundamental picture. It's just you know,
it's The reason stocks go up is because
people put their retirement savings in
the stock market. That's what That's
what happens, therefore stocks go up.
Yes, there's, you know, fluctuations,
variations along the way, but the path
of least resistance for equities is
always higher, at least for indexes,
especially with passive investing.
Yeah, index index path of least
resistance is higher. So, the stock
market bears little resemblance most of
the time to the economic fundamentals,
which is what you and I are interested
in, uh because we need to know what the
risks are in the real economy, therefore
have an idea, not just what the stock
market's doing, but we need to know what
the bond market's doing and uh and how
that plays into a whole bunch more than
just uh what what, you know, a couple of
stocks on the New York Stock Exchange or
the S&P 500 are doing. So, all right,
let's look at the the household survey
numbers by the actual numbers, like I
said, minus 226 in the household survey,
but the labor force dropped by almost
100,000, which was the second straight
monthly decline. And back in February,
the labor force was basically flat and
it had January population control
factors make create a discontinuity, but
it was down in December. So, the labor
force has been shrinking pretty
consistently here in 2026. That's one
reason why the adjusted unemployment
rate our adjusted unemployment rate hit
a new high is because we don't just we
don't just ignore these people that drop
out of labor force because we're
reasonably assuming they're dropping out
of the labor force given their consumer
pessimism because they see there are no
jobs. So, the official view of the labor
market as defined by the U3 rate is it's
pretty I mean the unemployment's 4.3% it
seems to have leveled off there. So, the
fact that we don't have any new jobs
anywhere, you know, whether it's the
establishment survey or the household
survey,
they they think it's not a big deal
because unemployment has been steady.
But it's only been steady because
hundreds of thousands of American
workers or former American workers drop
out of the official labor force because
they stopped looking for work
understanding there is no work to be
found. Therefore, we're missing a key
part of this deterioration. That's the
one that really lines up with consumer
sentiment. You look at the adjusted
unemployment rate and it looks a lot
worse than the regular unemployment
rate. So, it gets into the same
territory as consumer sentiment. What
consumers are saying is
we're so pessimistic on the labor market
even though we don't see widespread
layoffs,
um we're just dropping out of labor
force because nobody is hiring. If we do
lose our job, we're basically stuck. And
even those people who haven't lost a
job, they're increasingly concerned that
they could lose their job and if they
do, there is nowhere for them to go.
>> Yeah, Jeff and and we do have some
validation that you know, the the
headline number is not accurate. Now, we
of course we know it's going to get
revised and change and that doesn't
matter and then there's going to be the
big annual adjustment but how do we
reconcile the difference between the
nonfarm payroll and household survey,
University of Michigan survey and say,
is what we see in the labor market
correct? And we can go right back to
Thursday we had some preliminary data on
labor productivity and unit labor cost
and these are one of my favorite surveys
Jeff, you know this I think they're one
of yours too because nobody looks at
them but they really give you a big
consensus on if you're right or wrong.
So what did we see? Labor productivity
continued to slow down and decelerate.
Now this is not something you really
want to see because after companies lay
off assuming demand is constant or goes
up, you want to see productivity rising
and that tells you hey, we've got solid
demand here. So after businesses laid
people off
demand went down and the validation of
that is unit labor cost also decelerate.
It was kind of going sideways and also
it starts to drop off. Meaning employers
now realize there's so many people out
on unemployment that I don't have to
give you a raise and if you really
insist on one, I can get rid of you and
replace you. So you start looking at the
household survey, nonfarm payroll
report, you come right back to the labor
productivity data and tells you yes, the
economy is continuing to trend down and
the labor market is continuing to
weaken. Meaning what we should see is
inflation is not going to be an issue.
We know it follows of course wage unit
labor cost but it also means we should
see something in the interest rate
market that validates that too.
>> Well in the interest rate market you
have a sofa futures and forward rate
curves that have that frown shape that I
went over earlier this week which means
that the market expects that there's
some chance not a not a done deal but
there is some chance that the Federal
Reserve may raise rates at some point
this year which as we know would not be
completely unexpected because let's face
it they they are itching to raise rates
because the higher oil prices go, the
higher gasoline prices go, the more they
want to raise rates. This is
inflationary. This is inflationary. So,
the SOFR futures market says, there is a
decent chance the Fed, including you
know, other central banks around the
world, but the Fed, even the Fed might
raise rates this year, but then the
other part of the frown is that once
they raised rates, they won't They're
not going to raise them very far.
They're not going to keep them up there
for very long, and then they're going to
start cutting again. Now, right now the
the frown is relatively shallow, which
you would expect at this stage, which
means we're not looking at, you know,
the market isn't saying there's going to
be massive rate cuts in in early 2027.
What they're saying is that the
probability is there might be some rate
hikes here in the near term, and leading
back to rate cuts as the Fed
realizes that they made a huge mistake.
So, the rate market is saying, "Yeah, we
have weak unemployment, and you throw $5
gasoline on it. Whatever the central
banks do in the short run,
it's not going to last, because what you
just said, Steve, is hugely important
about productivity." You know, just big
picture terms. That's That's really it.
It's When you lay off workers, or you
cut back on workers, and cut back on
hours, cuz that's where productivity
comes from. You take the total amount of
hours that are estimated to have been
worked, and compare it to economic
output, right? That's productivity. So,
if you cut back on hours, you're
expecting productivity to rise, which
means you get more output out of the
amount of work that you're doing. That's
what recoveries always feature. You lay
off a bunch of workers, but then demand
starts to pick up, as Steve just said,
and so productivity starts to rise, and
you think, "Oh, I better start I better
start hiring more workers, because I'm
going to need them." And they can do
more when they when they show up. But
when they lay off workers and cut back
hours, and productivity doesn't pick up,
what that means is
"I need to cut even more workers to get
into that Demand didn't pick up. I've
got too many workers." That's really
what it says. So, in big picture terms,
you're right, Steve. Productivity,
University of Michigan, the household
survey, the unadjusted unadjusted
unemployment rate, this narrative about
a 2026 pickup, even before we got to $5
gasoline, just completely busted.
>> Yeah, so what it tells me, Jeff, is that
the entire economy right now is just
running on tax refund stimulus checks
because the reality is what we're seeing
signs of, and this is what we're really
been kind of watching for, is is the
energy shock going to push us into a
recession? Are we seeing evidence of
that? Yes, so the answers are we seeing
it in the labor market? Clearly. Are we
seeing it from a demand side? Yes. Are
we seeing it from employers? Yes. Are we
seeing it in interest rates? Yes. We're
seeing it in consumer sentiment surveys.
We're seeing all the evidence that money
is being redirected to spend on energy,
and businesses that we're hoping that
some of that money was going to find
their way into their doors, you know,
start to pull through this inventory.
It's not happening. So, you start
looking at private credit. What do we
hear from, you know, BlackRock just
yesterday? Is they're going to cut, you
know, 5% off the NAV of their publicly
traded fund. It's like, these are not
things that you do if the economy is
booming like the stock market is telling
you. These are things that happen during
a weakening labor market. Again, at some
point, yeah, can the market go higher?
Yeah, it can go crazy high. But at some
point, the day of reckoning of what's
going on in the underlying economy is
going to be very real.
>> Yeah, so let's, you know, let's talk
about Canada then for a minute because
the Canadian payroll report came out,
minus 17.7 thousand for the month of
April, shocking everybody because
everybody thought, okay,
you know, there was a downturn in
payrolls in Canada to start the year.
Again, same narrative. Last year's
weakness in Canada, the United States,
and everywhere else was all about
tariffs and trade uncertainty, whatever,
you know, trade wars, tariff
uncertainty, all that kind of stuff.
Once the system normalized to the tariff
levels, somewhere around summer time
heading into the end of the year, we
would see a pick up, especially in work,
you know, productivity was up. Um so, at
least in the short run. So, you know, we
were going to we expect we were supposed
to expect a pick up in the labor market,
therefore the overall economy, late
2025, and then 2026 would be the year of
the turnaround at least before we got to
the energy shock. But instead what we
see is that there was no pickup in late
2025 and as 2026 began, it began on the
wrong foot yet again. Canada is a
perfect example. Hit a minus 25,000
payroll loss in January then minus
84,000 in February. Big drop there and
everybody said, "Okay, that was just
some temporary maybe it was cold
weather, you know, it gets cold in
Canada we hear. So maybe that was just
cold weather in January and February
things will pick up but March, while
they there was a positive payroll for
March, it was only 14,000. So you lose
100,000 only get back 14. That's not a
good sign and then April, the latest
number that just came in on Friday,
minus 17,700. So you got three negatives
out of the four months here in 2026 and
the one that was positive was barely
positive and through all of that, Steve,
this is going to sound familiar, guess
what full-time jobs are doing in Canada?
Same thing they're doing here in the
United States. They are contracting.
Down by almost 50,000 month of April
versus the US, the household survey
full-time jobs, minus 400,000.
So what does that tell us, Steve? You
know the answer to this. You talk about
it all the time. The answer is companies
are cutting workers and those that
they're not cutting and laying off, they
are at the very least cutting back their
hours no matter what the establishment
survey said in its hours index and
average work week.
>> And you know, Jeff, despite all of that,
the Bank of Canada cut rates. When more
evidence that rate cuts don't do
anything any more than if the Fed were
to hike rates.
>> to 2 and 1/4% They are way down low.
They are they are well out of
restrictive territory. So everything
should be picking up, right, Steve?
>> Yeah, absolutely. So, you know, it's
interesting we talk about what the rates
market is saying but it really doesn't
matter if the Fed does raise rates or
lowers rates, it won't matter. The only
thing that will matter is if they do
drop rates, you know, the stock market's
going to go gangbusters on that. But in
terms of the real economy, you know, you
We we look at this energy shock and you
can see that the damage is now becoming
real and you know I I kind of asked over
the past couple weeks Jeff and you know
you heard me say this, when do we get to
that tipping point where even if energy
prices dropped and gas prices came down
and we know that's exactly what
President Trump wants. He wants energy
prices down, he wants interest rates
down, but are we past the point of no
return? Based on the data we're looking
at right now, the labor market is kind
of suggesting to me that we are.
>> Yeah, it's not definitive. I think
that's really it's there's we're in that
ambiguous gray area, right Steve? Where
it's you can't say for sure that we're
past the tipping point. You got a lot of
stuff that comes in contrary to
expectations. I mean consumer sentiment
is in the toilet, but then you can make
the case that consumer sentiment's been
in the toilet for over a year, so
um and I know you make that case all the
time, but consumer sentiment's down, the
markets are saying, you know, outside of
the stock market, there's lots to be
concerned about. Um so, you know, it's
you get the feeling that things are
moving in the wrong direction, but you
don't have that definitive signal. Of
course, by the time you get that
definitive signal, it's already way too
late to begin with. You have to deal
with balance of probabilities. And the
balance of probabilities by every single
factor, I mean you just went and checked
off all the boxes, right? And every
single one of those, even though there's
ambiguity and gray area, the balance of
probabilities are highly unfavorable.
And here's the thing, the most important
point we're that we're seeing in the uh
labor market numbers as well as uh you
know, gasoline, is things are getting
worse. They're moving in the wrong
direction. Gasoline most of all, we're
escalating further into an energy shock.
We're escalating further into a downturn
in the labor market. Higher unemployment
across, you know, not just the US and
Canada, but other places too. Mexico GDP
contracted by a substantial amount in
the first quarter, which is a proxy for
US demand. So, the Mexicans are saying,
"Hey, things are not going well up north
either." So, you look in one place after
another after another, while there's
ambiguity and gray area, the balance of
probabilities have shifted in the
downside case and have done so in very
broad and widespread fashion. And again,
that's before we get to the full weight
of $5 gasoline.
>> Yeah, Jeff, so what you know, you look
at the you know, if we throw out the
nonfarm payroll number out of the
picture here, of course we know no
matter what it was printing today, stock
market was going to go up. But if you
look at everything out outside of that,
the trend is indeed going the wrong way.
It's been going the wrong way. And right
now, nothing appears to be changing
that. The risk is once the stimulus from
the tax reform goes away, the question
is what happens to the economy then? And
right now, it looks like we're set to
take another leg lower.